welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
all right check-ins
yeah I'm feeling a little heartbroken at
the moment it's pretty intense
so welcome to the stoah I'm Peter
Limburg the Stewart of the stoah and a
stoah is the place where we cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
nice edge of this moment and today we
have Phil Chen whose game be a superstar
who was in Toronto was currently in sort
of the monastic Academy near Toronto at
the moment or what is to be the monastic
Academy and he will be hosting today's
session so I'll hand it to him maybe you
can kind of just introduce how it's
gonna go today Phil and we can go from
there
let me just Mar you to unmute yourself
there you go okay thanks Peter
apologize in this Buddhist monastery the
internet might not be great so Peter
might need to jump in sometime hopefully
you guys can hear me okay yeah I'm still
feeling a little nervous a little tired
yeah very excited to facilitate this
session with Jordan Hall today I think
I'm very grateful for him to be on this
earth he's influenced a lot of my
thinking especially around game B and
the deep code so today this session will
run similar to previous situational
assessments Jordan will spend some time
giving his situational assessment then
we will break out to a QA where you'll
answer some of your questions and how
that will work is if you do have a
question please write it in the chat box
and I will call on you to unmute and ask
your question if you do want to me to
read the question please indicate it
when you write it down so that's a brief
introduction on what is going to happen
today so now I want to pass it off to
Jordan guess what is it live for you
and you yeah you're gonna meet yourself
now Jordan thank you I've been
contemplating this and trying to figure
out what's a way to well what is the
most salient thing to remote relevant
thing to put into this into this space
and the sense that that came to me was a
little bit like folding and the folding
of layers of Earth on top of each other
the crease strata so by the way I just
realized in my mind I just activated a
little bit of de lawyers up there but um
but my sense is that that we will not
meaningfully exit the the liminal moment
the at least in the West began with the
way the corona virus impacted our system
we are beginning to move through the
sort of the psychological adjustment
phase where there's a sense now people
having adjusted to a some kind of new
state or some kind of new condition and
of course in that same context that
adjustment also involves a surfacing of
different dispositions in that context
right so we have kind of people also
pulling apart but they're pulling apart
in this new context and what I'm finding
myself noticing is is is looking out
ahead again my horizon is moving in the
direction of months three four five six
months out as opposed to sort of what's
right in front of me because it feels
like the things right in front while
meaningful
are settling there's a settling
happening there so on the one hand III
do continue to watch the events that are
unfolding and I think even I apologize
if it's not in this venue but relatively
recently I remember talking about the
thing to be watching now is the is the
co-creative or the code dynamic forces
between the balkanization and
authoritarianism as they pull back and
forth against each other I'm so mega
like a very simple simple example is
what happened in Orange County with the
beaches so we had a some small loosening
restrictions some small loosening of
authoritarianism that unlocked a
significant energy of people wanting to
have more well-to-do what something some
energy that had been constrained about
that authoritarianism which resulted in
a whole lot of people going to the
beaches
what's then interesting enough generated
a pushback like a stronger level of
authoritarianism which in this case was
the governor in California said it okay
Orange County beaches are closed again
but and this is the thing to keep your
eye on which then led to a pushback with
say County Sheriff saying we now are not
going to enforce state law and then
these things move back and forth so one
of the things I think is very useful to
keep your eye on over the next few
months is that dynamic at all levels
like all the fractal levels even in your
own mind but I I found my attention
pulling forward if I look for where big
waves are coming in particularly where
waves are beginning to we'll be
reinforcing each other late summer and
early fall seems like a place to be
focusing enormous attention right now we
have at least three distinct
vectors through distinct ways like the
desert in some sense independent but are
also very meaningfully overlap so we of
course have the the concern or the
inquiry or the question about a
quote-unquote second way in the end of
viral direction and whether that second
wave comes from one of nine different
directions and other ones at least nine
different ways that could show up the
key inside is the degree to which you
would see a resurgence or a surge in
cases potentially more more lethal cases
that would then shift consciousness away
from a okay this thing is over let's
relax and settle back into something on
the other side of virus space into a Oh
what do we do with this how do we deal
with it and how do we respond so when
the zero to one shifts in consciousness
at the same time with a both or the
bordering uncertainty the the
implications of the perturbation at the
economy level will be cascading through
in that timeframe so these things have a
was it a general thing I've been
watching very closely said something
like modern economies can stop like a
sports car but they restart like a train
actually there's a this thing stopped
watching the implications of all these
different supply chain disruptions from
the demand side than by the supply side
and then back on the demand side
financial side stimulus side
unemployment like all these different
interventions there's a series of
ripples that are cascading through very
large number of different systems and
those will continue to play out and play
out and play out and kind of the thud of
that won't really be felt until late
summer so when you get into late summer
early fall well-formed sort of finally
at last be getting some sense of what we
did with with the implications of the
choices we made last month actually
unlikely to be so you're gonna find
yourself where we may very well find
ourselves in a circumstance where
there's a gosh I thought the viruses in
the review mirror even though we're
aware of the story of second wave it
doesn't matter embodied sense of it will
be we're past it when in fact it may
actually come back into a desire to be
perceived as more salient while now the
impact
implications that actually settled into
something which is now felt deeply
across a lot of different strata so
those two those two waves could very
easily become highly reinforcing a
simple example might be a okay now we
need to go back into lockdown
but now a stronger a very strong sense
that fuck you I'm not going to lock down
what exactly happens there and the
tension between those two of course is
perfectly aligned to build but of course
at least in the context of the United
States then you also have the political
side specifically the election so in in
late summer early fall we'll be entering
into a principle provisionally a formal
choice of who the Democratic nominee is
and a the game is afoot in terms of what
the election will look like and so I
would imagine that the energy underneath
that curve will be will be higher like
step function higher than it is now and
build it like accelerating towards the
fever pitch and where we'll be in late
October so then that's another one right
and of course the implications of the
choice making around economy and the
choice making around virus shows up in
the context of election and vice versa
and of course in the context of election
the moment how I say it be it
patient to play political games to gain
political capital by trading on fear and
or real implications in virus space and
economic space will be inescapable and
then we can I guess finally layer on
something that's a little bit more
difficult to track because the
trajectory most of the trajectory is
invisible or difficult to see and the
way that evolves is equally difficult to
trace that's it the geopolitical level
so I imagined that most people now are
aware of the Wuhan Institute of Virology
origin narrative this has gone from by
the way it originally showed up in China
so shortly after the the virus was
became known in China so as it went from
being the thing that was happened do the
thing that was being perceived
there was actually explosion in Chinese
social media with the this is a
human-made virus narrative which got
shut down like clipped one night so the
search was going like this and the next
night he was effectively gone and then
and it was relatively silent that can
burst through in a number of different
small areas mostly futurists types were
head connections to China who are aware
of the previous narrative in research
its kind of trace that it went
underground up until gosh I guess about
couple weeks ago and now it's beginning
to burst back into the mainstream in now
in fact not just bursting into the
mainstream of consciousness but now
becoming part of the geopolitical
fencing match and so the dynamic between
the West the Trump administration in
particular and China which is not a
whole thing a China's a whole complex of
different groups and forces it's quite
likely to continue to escalate as we
move into the summer and fall but much
more complex but at least in principle
could add to this wave spicy could have
a fourth wave that builds in that exact
same time frame so I think that's kind
of a good place to stop it's but it's
very general but in terms of orientation
the feeling I have is a feeling of maybe
this
a certain class of rollercoaster where
you go up and you do a big dive but
that's actually not the real dive like
you feel your stomach come up into your
throat but then you get the real big one
I get the feeling that's gonna kind of
be like that and that that notion of
layers of like you know there's an info
leanness that we were in a liminal space
and we're almost coming to terms at the
liminal set but before we can even and
by the way I wouldn't necessarily
recommend that we try to exit liminal
space but before we can come to terms
with it there's actually infolding
another layer that comes on top and
actually builds a strata of where we're
at and to the extent possible it would
be by my sense at least that to be able
to orient to that pace or into that
dynamic and build the skillfulness of
agency sovereignty in that context and
meta I mean not as just as an individual
book like this but groups of people who
are beginning to orient and be able to
cohere around the recognition that it is
only in creating relationality
discernment integrity sense making and
then increasingly collaborative fective
collaborative choice making that we can
begin to form a ship that can actually
sail is increasingly choppy seas okay so
I suppose that's that for now
all right Jordan thank you for setting
the background there's a whole bunch
people who came in so I might reiterate
the instructions again we have like 79
people here so if you have a question
please write it in the chat box
I'll call upon you to unmute and ask
your question if you want me to read
your question just indicate and I will
read it out aloud for you
unfortunately there's with so many
people we might not get to all your
amazing questions so yeah just letting
you know that I think I'll start this in
asking a question around like the first
thing that came out to my mind is like
oh I wasn't seeing oh this potential for
different ways coming at the same time
is there a good way to I guess prepare
for that or watch out for that to see if
it's actually coming
because the the way you ask the question
it shifted for me so the first part of
the question felt like he was a how do
you had to prepare for it how do you the
wave is coming and how do you prepare
yourself so when the wave hits you're
not thrown over and then the second was
shifted in the direction of more in the
rest of sense making how do we have we
become capable of perceiving it
in the context of perceiving it and the
medicine is sort of the same medicine
we've been talking about for quite some
time which is just to continue to
cultivate your since making Network a
very simple approach which we have
available to us right now would be to go
back and try to identify the the nodes
of the individuals and in that really
individuals but actually our collections
of individuals that did the best job in
january/february and and have continued
to maintain qualities you could just
kind of go back and do an audit and find
individuals who really seemed to had
high quality perception and maintain
integrity of their communication through
that arc and you know gathered them just
write them down what I'm in a
spreadsheet or something keep an eye on
them
by the way and this is actually a
technique that I use quite often the
exact inverse is also quite useful so
you think oh ok for example I think I
even mentioned this in a facebook thread
whenever I see the word debunked I
assume that it means exactly the
opposite which it means pay attention to
the thing that is being claimed to be
debunked it doesn't mean that the thing
that is claimed to be debunked is true
but it means it is pay attention here
like dig here a little bit more deeply
because somebody somewhere and maybe not
consciously really doesn't want to pay
attention to that
so there's circumstances also where
there was there are sources of sense
making it mostly these are no sources of
news that are so obviously bad signal I
said this but not just noise though
they're actually extremely high quality
signal in the inverse direction so this
was also useful like have that and where
you see that almost clumsy effort to
steer your attention you can also use
that as signal so ok cool I've seen I'm
seeing the signs of desires or efforts
to in the war on sense making to control
the narrative to bind my mind to a
particular frame ok great I now have
enough capacity to actually use that as
a counter signal and that Orient's me
more effective like I'm sort of able to
parkour off the wall and bounce back
into the direction so I think both these
are quite true and then you know it's
it's a the the basic would you call it
like cross-training you know tune into
yourself check in with your body see
where your own narratives pop up the way
that you delude yourself the way that
you avoid certain things and continue to
kind of build that because over the next
couple of months we do in some sense
have a slowing down I would propose or
at least
I expect so this is a good opportunity
to actually take some deep breaths and
kind of rebuild out those capacities and
retune your since they can environment
it's a at the individual level in terms
of preparation actually being prepared I
would actually take the more aggressive
approach this is an energy this is a
wave of energy that's coming through and
what would be ideal is to actually
create turn yourself into a sprint
turn yourself into an engine that can
find a way it can convert that energy
into something that then directs back
out in a way that creates the change you
want to see in the world what exactly
that looks like this certainly
non-trivial but again you can always use
the basic rule there something of how
that shows up in yourself and then
there's something that shows up in your
relationships as that becomes a larger
fractal so practicing teamwork and
learning how to actually produce results
and by the way thinking about how do I
say this
there's a there's an inhibition on
change and an additional possibility
that shows up in our own sensibility of
what is in fact actually possible most
of the time almost time oftentimes we
limit what could happen ourselves like
we preempt change by inhibiting our own
willingness to try and by the way in
many cases that's actually perfectly
reasonable that's actually a very good
choice most of the time carefulness is
the right response
but sometimes boldness is the right
response and so sort of practicing
boldness might be a very useful skill
you know rock climbing or whitewater
rafting or is it just metaphors but or
in fact actually practical but
practicing the fine art of learning how
and when to move into a it's time to
attack it's time to make bold moves into
possibility and feel that that energy
feels like you this Chronos Kairos
distinction capoeira yeah if you have
access to
capoeira domain that might be a very
good skill like practice learning how to
move from the dance that is the dance to
the music to the dance that has suddenly
morphed into kicking somebody's ass or a
whole group of people has asked still to
the music but all very metaphorical by
I think that's probably the most
fundamentally the most globally true
piece we can get into details if you'd
like appreciate that answer many great
questions coming in the chat so thanks
everyone
what's calling to me is the one that
Brad the blinds can you unmute and ask
your question
I can hear me all right great so Jordan
thanks for doing this
my question was mainly around the game
be seen I see a lot around group
coherence and sense-making which is very
much needed but I'm finding as we're
trying to self-organize there's very
little work or discussion about group
cohesion meaning the ability for a group
to stick together so once more about
sense making the other is about the
ability to stick together they're very
different do you have any starting
points or suggestions about what
materials guides or areas would you look
into for people who want to self
organize and focus on group cohesion
well I that's not the way I don't really
think in that fashion I don't have a I
don't read books to to get guidance so I
don't have that but what I would what I
would suggest is that the generally
speaking the answer to cohesion is
embodied complexity which generally
speaking means actually do something so
for example if you've ever done like an
outward-bound project program you can
get 12 people and you have to Matt
navigate from point A to point B through
trial like you have to learn how to you
know climb a wall and descend down the
other side of the wall and build a raft
and cross the river
you know actually solve real problems
what's amazing is that that's a
completely made-up domain like you don't
know particular need to do it but that
like these micro it's it's the the
notion that the complex environments
have these micro relationality
sorry I'm trying to in my mind I'm
looking at you I may actually be looking
off into the corner so so to build
cohesion requires to actually undergo
something in reality together and the
more embodied it is the actual the
better so the old day raised bed garden
together write software together that
has a closed-loop mean that it actually
has to go from ideation to ship to to a
point where the world actually verifies
that you did a good job those kinds of
practices write a document together
where you're delivering that document
out into reality you know the idea of a
little loop the a loops back to the oh
right but it loops out of the entity the
entity is the OOD a reality is the ADA
oh and that's that that linkage right
there so the practices of cohesion
building are always have to be embodied
practices in direct relationship with
reality iteratively like just do them in
amps the stakes I can build increase the
stakes and as you increase the stakes
and the most cohesive groups are like
the Navy SEALs and how do they do that
they go through buds train ignites the
stakes are very very high and very
intense and though what they generally
do isn't meaningful and carrying a log
through the mud or getting on a boat and
you know as the waves are crashing isn't
meaningful but the the reality is that
to practice against reality to practice
against nature such that the group has
to discover its embodied capacity as
humans to learn how to trust and how to
build the strength of the binding
there's
kind of moved from covalent bonds to
ionic bonds and then providing bonds
tits reelect romantic bonds that is done
in doing
you
very cool um sorry I'm trying to find
the question Jacob could you unmute
yourself and ask your question sure
hello Jordan can't see you so what's
your sense with what's going on the
spiritual layout since you spoke on the
stoah about a spiritual crisis and also
as you're talking and sensing that the
answer is gonna be something to do with
a kind of listening leave it at that
what I do notice as I expected would be
the case that more people are losing
their minds more fully and
that would be I think probably the most
most meaningful or most uh I say this
right
it is simultaneous
most obvious but also more suddenly the
most relevant aspect of that notion of
the spiritual crisis like even the term
spiritual crisis is a new way of
describing a psychotic break isn't
really would good with thinking about it
gosh it's such a weird actually I'm
feeling a certain pressure which is
interesting like there's a
sense is that there's a seeking or a
looking or an effort to discover
something that is normally not seeable
something that is normally quite good at
hiding itself from our view but
nonetheless plays a decisive role in in
influencing our choice making what just
popped into my head is a really nice
yeah when is it the veil is very thin
right now that's a nice way of putting
it
and in fact I think that the physicality
of it is actually quite Neal I was just
reading an article that Jim Wright will
link to about the psychedelic
consciousness and capitalism ubi is was
talking about and I think it's a nice
way of thinking about it the
consciousness is always a psychedelic
consciousness everything we're in is
always set and setting and that there's
something about the nature of the
disruption the set and setting that is
reactivating the ambient reality of the
psychedelic nature of consciousness and
that there's a journey or seeking for
the ability to perceive the invisible
hand and how that invisible hand has
been constraining our consciousness our
psychology but also our perception and
our sensing in ourselves to put us on a
train which is to say a directionality
over which we have very little choice as
opposed to in an open field or in a
desert to use the toys a metaphor we can
we're in fact forced to wander the
desert I think that links very closer to
the thing that I love that with which is
that there was a at the objective level
a hammer something that hit us and shook
things up one of the characteristics oh
that's shaking things up is it's almost
like a pain and echolocation in the
spiritual realm of the psycho spiritual
realm and if you slow down and listen
you'll notice that as the echoes are
bouncing off of everything and therefore
the the illusion of normality is so
obviously impossible to establish you
can actually get a perception of
structures that ordinarily are very
difficult to perceive
and this will tend to give rise to more
more basic energies so erotic energy for
example will tend to show up more
powerfully because it's more fundamental
but it says it's more founded in longer
deeper things and so you should expect
to see erotic energy building and and
and then shifting in and controlling
choice-making more fully which is
actually a very interesting thing to
think about and a to degree to which we
want to become agents in this story true
the degree to which we can taste that
the building or fundamental energy and
ourselves and understand where it wants
to go and become vehicles for its
flowing into the world we can up
regulate it and allow it to express
itself which minute of course the BR
mmm you may have already answered this
Jordan but I'm thinking about pushing
into some positive like Kim's question
yourself yeah I do Orden you just went
blank I'm just gonna assume that you're
still there you'll see I can't see you
yeah I can see you on the side right my
question is kind of long the lines of
what they're doing you ain't talking
about us moving the it feels like in
this sort of build-up and this sort of
shaking shaking the web and it going out
further us getting a little freedom in
the summer us getting then then shaking
up again and then the election coming at
the business of time it's like a really
specific and special time that we can be
paying attention to and what are there
ways we can maximize this period yeah I
just just to just do the greatest
advantage of the greatest good thank you
yeah thank you uh the thing that popped
into my head and I think I really like
the way that you used a particular
metaphor
it's the way that you said it for me was
this inertia shaking the web the idea of
a spider at the center of a web and and
things hitting it and shaking it and
kind of coming through our feet the next
thing that popped in my head was just
I'm not sure that was linearly related
to what you were saying but it feels
like it's very important is to say okay
look here's the reality every
institution is made up I think it's
super important about the game a game B
language was invented to present into
consciousness the reality that other
than those things that are strictly
natural like biological in nature or
physics everything else is a game that
we made up we're playing the money game
we're putting the government game we're
playing the how we live in family game
like all that stuff and it's okay to
notice that there ain't
buddy in charge and it's okay to realize
that there are no adults in the room I
don't know if you've spent time
interacting with the people who are
officially leaders they really aren't
any more mature wise or sophisticated or
capable than strategic or intelligent
than anybody else you've ever met
on occasion there's a few folks out
there there's obviously the average
variance but pick a group of 180 people
who kind of gather together you've got a
pretty sizable slice of the whole human
population broadly speaking on these in
terms of competence not necessarily in
terms of perspective or background and
that's not that it's not grounds for
concern this I think is the point is it
is grounds for responsibility okay we're
playing a game the game sucks and it
gets it's getting worse right it was it
has all kinds of negative constraints in
particular produces people in a very
unfortunate way but now we were able to
see that it's also not particularly
effective at doing the things that is
supposed to do like managing simple
things like making sure masks are
produced and delivered to places like
even if the thing it's it claims to do
well which is material economics it's
beginning to have real challenges okay
cool
why don't we design a new game and here
what I would do is I would I would
insert the framework and the mechanism
that I put out ever so long ago we
should say look there's kind of three
layers and they're very distant almost
like temperature layers in the ocean
there's the game be story but the gaming
story is not yet right here like I don't
expect at least I may be wrong but I
don't expect that we can just sort of
teleport to game B teleportation is
awesome but I think it mostly just lives
in Star Trek we have to journey to game
B so there's a there's a there's a
journey and there's a transition it's
that transition B is crucial and the
transition B will inevitably look the
first step we'll have two really
interesting characteristics one
characteristic is that will look a lot
like where we are so in many ways it
will look like a it would be India Jason
possible so a it will be possible and B
be adjacent nice wouldn't be a step and
you can look around and say okay things
haven't changed that much on the other
hand things will have changed completely
the metaphor that I really liked is that
there's a this this is a this is a
parting of the Red Sea and leaving Egypt
moment this is not a arriving in the
promised land moment and the thing is is
that as the Red Sea is parting you're
still in Egypt and as even as you're
going across the Red Sea Egypt's just
right over there you look over your
shoulder you can still see Egypt but at
the same time you've left Egypt that's
those are very very important like to
recognize that distinction and if you
think about that in terms of
practicality if we're designing a new
game particularly we even this call
those who ultimately perceive it we're
gonna want everybody else to play or at
least a whole lot of people to play
which means it's gotta look like things
they know how to play it's unlikely
we're going to be able to teleport away
from money in a single move because
people's don't really know how to do
things yet without using money cool but
we can change money and particularly can
change money in two or three very
important ways one was just like used to
use be at ubi as a metaphor ubi is like
but the veil is thin the veil on ubi is
so freaking finis incredible just right
there and this article that I was
referring by the way which is very wordy
they kind of gets the point is you guys
are kind of moved that it may actually
seem very much like stuff we already
understand really well but it does it
changes some things at the bottom line
very profoundly and so it's one of these
characteristics where in a single move
you could sever a lot of stuff we just
have never needed but you could also
change the thing that we're doing in a
way that the superficial level seems
very ordinary but actually is profoundly
changing at the bottom like the
generator function reshaping the Fitness
landscape or the topology and so
whatever would happen is that then there
would be a natural migration to a new
place as you would if you imagine that
the game be is uphill right now you
would tilt the table so game B is
downhill people are still gonna end up
having to wander through the desert to
get there but and
being much more my natural direction of
the environment so to me the move is and
where I'm certain focus on my own
personal energy is on endeavoring to
identify what would be the
characteristics of a material shift and
then in the game that we are currently
playing is potentially available now or
would be made available as the moment
increases in intensity and breadth that
is nonetheless in the adjacent possible
how do we sever those things that just a
stupid just should go away and then how
do we create and redesign where
superficially it's not that different
from what we're very used to but at the
generator function at the bottom is
completely different and it comes from a
different place it comes from scared
from abundance rather than scarcity as
the sort of disciplines been putting it
I hope that was helpful so for me I seen
this question a couple of times last
nice to be from Joe can you sure hi
Jordan my question comes about in one of
your recent talks you mentioned or
someone asked you about Eve on Ilitch
and you said that you got most right on
education so I've been reading him since
the last time I spoke about him
so the question goes like this it says
so paying attention is the sort of game
B crowd and other sort of anti
institutional thinkers it sort of
reveals a world which is existentially
fragile it actually punishes virtue and
it's constantly transferring wealth from
people who are vulnerable to people who
are physicians of strategic leverage my
question is how is it possible for a
person and in my case a young person
about to enter into this world as a
laborer to participate in the world
without an overwhelming feeling of
resentment for the social structure
which you inherit and also the people
which drive this structure
and continue to extract resources from
it so Peter actually put it in other
words he said what is right relationship
with resentment look like when you have
to participate in that which you resent
nice
that's beautiful like Oh neat you
actually made a very nice distinction
between resentment and resent Amal so
avoid resent him Oh
like like really seriously deeply resent
Aman is what happens when you have
internalized resentment and have created
a narrative and ideology that how much
for this right it's a it's a
circumstance where you ultimately end up
actually participating in your own
enslavement by virtue of believing the
agency occurs by pointing a blaming
finger aggressively so relent amok says
this this thing that I'm entering into
sucks but it's but but I'm so weak and
so overwhelmed I cannot possibly change
it so what it does is instead of instead
of having real agency it invents false
agency and says that oh well pointing my
finger at it and complaining vigorously
about it is agency per se and the
feeling of agency replaces actual
agencies this is the trap and of course
at that point you're hopelessly trapped
because you also are easily manipulated
and to just you know you blame them they
blame you everybody feels like they're
their self righteously like exercising
their feeling and resentment and and
nothing changes so what I would say is
to recognize it's such a beautiful thing
as listening to the way you're
describing it the feeling of resentment
just like the feelings of anger and of
fear is a perception first and foremost
of a state of reality that has a
wrongness to it and a an awakening or a
an activation of an energy and self to
respond to that wrong
that's what that energy is the moment
you begin the process of Meerut izing it
could be in trouble let me you attach
meaning-making to perception is where
things get challenging and so the simple
answer is to say first and foremost
allow the feeling to be the feeling but
do not attempt to attach the feeling to
the way that you make meaning about the
feeling particularly to the degree to
which you're you're engaging in meaning
making third person to the degree to
which somebody else's story is the story
that you're using to make sense of your
own feeling who that somebody is it can
be post-structuralist sorr it could be
libertarians it doesn't matter as soon
as somebody else's narrative is what
you're using to make sense up to make
meaning out of your feeling you're
definitely gonna be in trouble okay
great I think it's perfectly appropriate
we're gonna teen is accurate to feel
resentment in that context that is the
appropriate emotion feeling but then you
say okay well what does resentment do or
resentment does is resentment Orient's
me towards the wrongness okay cool
now I know which direction is if I'm
sailing a boat I know which direction
the wind is coming from but then you
have to be very serious then you have to
say okay strategic effectiveness cannot
be surrendered for a feeling or a
sensation of effectiveness I have to
actually recognize that the only way to
resolve the resemble is to actually
resolve the situation that I find myself
in and that's has to be recognized as
decidedly non-trivial in fact it may
take generations
I may be fucked in terms of this thing
but I may be able to cast the movement
that Orient's enough people to be able
to slog directionally such that three
generations hence this thing that is
wrong is no longer happening and that's
a very powerful mindset a powerful mind
said that dissing doesn't become
powerlessness at the inability of
snapping your fingers and making things
happen
it says okay great I am now in for the
long haul I may be wandering through the
desert for three generations before we
get to the promised land
what does one step in the right two
should look like and you can take a
breath at that like if I made one step
in the right direction against these
kind of headwinds against these currents
that are trying to push me in the wrong
direction
that's an enormous thing and of course
what ends up happening if you get to
talk about this elsewhere is that if
you're if you're in a disaster River and
most people are being pulled along with
the current and you were ever so
slightly going against the current the
ability to see everybody else does ever
so slightly going against the current
gets a lot easier and then you try to
find ways of saying okay great
there is no way that I can do this
myself that there are possibly ways for
us to do this together
and that's that's it like again it's
very metaphorical but the point is to
really really get into that deep sense
of recognizing that the resentment don't
attach yourself to narratives
particularly third-party narratives
other people's stories about what is the
basis or the orientation of that
resentment second recognized that as a
feeling it is real important and valid
and honorable but its value is to orient
you towards what is wrong and to give
you activate your energy to begin the
process of swimming upstream against it
to push against it and then to recognize
it maybe generations before that problem
is solved your job is to always step in
the right way and perhaps to die trying
well that was great
I like the sailing analogy and it brings
up one of the questions from Michael's
Sicilian Sicily on yes hello my fourth
question is what are you force about the
new roles and identities we have to stop
playing whedon and training and maybe
employing to sail and navigate this
increasingly shopping see like the booka
booka well something important talking
about the game the game be well as but
what but what steps can we take now and
start training and playing we grow new
roles and identities like reframing and
renaming old roles or completely new
roles
yeah so the the thing that the first
pops in my head is this notion of stem
cell and to make that a little bit more
clear what I mean is there's there is
potential or portent eeeh and there's
actual and I would say one of the
primary addictions or maladaptive the
world in which we currently live is an
extraordinary bias towards identities
that are actual oh gosh I'm sorry I have
so many things going on in my mind
visually I'm having a hard time
remembering one what is already in your
head and two what I've already said so
what I mean by actual is this like this
have you ever played a brand-new video
game like you you're you're playing a
game I don't know if civilization or
something like that where you've never
played it before and so you or puzzle
I'll use purse so I've got I've got a
puzzle it's in the box I take the pieces
I dump them out on the table and there's
a moment of intense mystery oh I wonder
what this is gonna be that's firstness
in the personal sense and then there's
the moment at which there's a transition
from that to something that has now a
bounded domain there now there's an
actuality to it you found the corners
and the edges and the puzzle now has a
certain ah whatever happens it's gonna
be inside this box that's the transition
into the actual then there's the the
movement from the second mister third
miss and again in the personal sense
which is the process of getting really
really good at optimizing for that
puzzle are you sort by colors yet if I
were the what are the shapes that matter
like you begin the process of solving
the puzzle so our world is a world that
lives in third ness it's a world where
identities are identities that are
optimized for being pieces of a machine
that is itself optimized for solving
problems they were pulled out of the
mystery whale well before our
grandparents were born okay in this new
environment in the new environment there
is an equipoise between the potentially
actual we always returned back to the
bottom of the you I guess to use that
that terminology we become we go into
being tissues we become heart cells or
nerve cells in a
organ organism and then we return back
to being stem cells and so the current
primary identity is that identity of the
polymorph the identity of the stem cell
the identity of the thing that is is
fundamentally oriented towards the
relationship between the potential the
actual it has the capacity to sense in
the sum of the possibilities that are
emerging and it's not in any way yet
binding them or constrained them by
preconceived fractured structures in the
actual but is actually allowing them yes
a blurry potentiality thank you allowing
them to show up and then has a
skillfulness at in the time that is
right in the time it is is is not too
fast or too slow to render them into the
actual but they're not gonna become
bound to that so that I'd say is the
fundamental now of course what that
means is that the actualizations
identity is that in some sense we can
put a pin and write a name against our
now very large I wanted to say infinite
but I have to hesitate because it's not
strictly infinite it's that thing that
is the limit as X approaches infinity
there will be innumerable identities and
one will flit in and out of them and may
in fact spend many - you may be a given
identity structure for four minutes and
then flip to another one in serial and
and you may pull in and out of them as
well and I think that's the key find
that that notion and the lawyers
actually nailed this in the PostScript
since inside of the controls if you
gonna double click on that and look at
what early 90s language for that looks
like it creates a nice paralyzed but I
think that's the essence of it all right
the essence is a building fundamental
skillfulness and being a stem cell and
being sensitive to the relationship
between possibility in actuality and
learning how to develop a meshwork
and to spontaneously form the identity
structures in yourself and in others in
relation ality that are necessary to
construct a machine that can actualize
potentialities in bespoke in response to
what's happening now but never become
bound in them and then be able to revert
back very fluidly and by the way this is
not in the least of theoretical this is
the these skills have been developed in
say for example in
in the Special Operations community over
the past 20 or 30 years because of the
necessity of not binding yourself to
particular skills and actually learning
how to become hyper generalists like
hyper competent generalists who can
build because they're so hyper competent
as generalists they can optimize for
specifics in bespoke locations solve the
problem on the ground that is actual and
requires that level of specializations
and sometimes you need to become a
plumber and then come back up I think
about that again very practical I think
how quickly these days we can learn new
skills
I actually thought it'd be a very nice
game to play as to ask people what new
skills have you learned under quarantine
and it should be many like because you
can watch a youtube video and learn
stuff fast these days like I actually
built a whole cedar hot tub and learned
how to be a plumber learn how to do
electrician behind my electrician I mean
not the whole array of plumbing an
electrician but for that sub-domain
skills that I had zero coming in and
actually built a real thing that keeps
water warm and doesn't leak by watching
youtube videos and think about that and
everybody can do that now so to build
the skill learning about learning like
metal learning to build metal learning
as a competence and to be able to access
the universal flow of people who have
competence in all these subdomains who
can render that into curricula that you
can absorb quickly iterate on in
practice and actually build functional
skill like good enough to do the thing
you're trying to do that's the future
right I'm excited because I think it
connects to question around liminality
this one that Peter put the first
question in the chat that we finally
could get back to it so the passage of
Peter to ask us a question all right
feels like this one has already been
answered but maybe I'll ask it anyways
cuz the frame might inspire some
thoughts this is the very first question
so one how are you building right
relationship with the liminal and B how
do you recommend others in the general
sense build right relationship with the
liminal
okay so let's see well I certainly
you
obviously first slow down the liminal is
one of these things where it's
it's subtle and easily disturbed and
learning how to not muddy the waters and
to move slowly through the water so that
you can perceive what is in fact
actually being expressed is first and
foremost the liminal teaches us how to
perceive the luminol so as we build
skillfulness and not muddying the waters
and not creating ripples and then simply
listen to what is being taught always
everywhere every aspect of experience
contains the lesson we find that every
opportunity the experience is contains
in it the lesson that is enabling us to
increase our capacity for relationality
with the liminal
more intense the experience
the more skillful skillfulness is needed
to hold
that stillness so as to allow the lesson
to unfold itself in us
which by the way in many cases also
takes a great deal of time and so it is
not simply the case of being able to
listen in the moment but to actually
learn the skillfulness of holding the
piece in oneself to allow the lesson to
unfold over what may be days or weeks or
months or years
there's lots of all the classic words
humility peace
gratitude deserve saying serve a key and
I have been sitting I think or were
doing spinning some the next time just
grabbing words like gratitude I'm trying
to dust them off and recover them
gratitude is a it's a state that is a
disposition I'm going to do is a
relationship with the whole of
possibility you can have gratitude for
something but that is very much a
denatured example and you can work your
way back you can imagine things for
which you are grateful to remind you of
what it what the feeling of gratitude is
but the the practice of gratitude is the
practice of actually placing yourself in
the pure state of gratitude in
relationship to the whole of reality
without regard to a particular object
the same thing is true the course of
humility and so to practice those and
learn how to flex and exercise those
muscles I think is it a useful skill in
this context
so what I'm getting from that is the
felt sense reality is something like the
liminal just really sink into that and
sort of map that over with the concept
yeah the concept feels off to me it's no
yeah it's it's more like the competence
the conformity the grasping to sink in
and then she simply had become too have
become grown into it right awesome like
we're two minutes to 11 here and there
was many more questions and the chats
that I feel bad that we can't get to I
think we're gonna wrap it up here and
appreciate all the questions you want
one more yeah some reason I thought
there's one more question that would be
it's at least available the energy is
pretty Wow is there any specific thing
of life in you right now that you want
to say sorry I can't do that
I'm entirely live all right Peter Peter
Wayne let's find a voice that I haven't
ever heard okay or over King maybe work
backwards cuz I don't want to appoint
anybody out if someone doesn't want to
be one too that is there is there a
voice out there that that I've never met
you and I've never heard your voice and
you feel my emotion that you'd like to
say something
Nicole what Lydia beautiful so Lydia
that seems right she needs to be unmuted
I think
hello there hi thank you very much for
allowing me to participate in this
discussion I don't have the the
multi-faceted ability with language that
is being demonstrated by the level of
conversation here but I'm getting what
meaning I can in what way that I can in
my isolation and Quarantine it is simply
not realistic for me to live in a
goal-oriented world where I must learn
to build a skill like making a new cedar
deck or even pursuing anything right now
I'm absolutely incapable of it all that
I really want to do is extract meaning
at a much deeper level and those of you
who have the mechanistic skills to be
able to manipulate language like this
I'm in awe of you but it's simply
outside of my my capabilities however
thank you for letting me put my two
cents in I mean I said that the you know
the thing that I feel when I want to
hear that is this I guess I mean I guess
if I suppose Rosen's me as a desire to
build a skill is to build skillfulness
which is to
you
increased capacity in any way at all of
any sort so to choose to participate in
this particular call and as you say to
be gathering the meaning that you can is
the sort of thing at least that I was
endeavouring to talk about but I like
also the fact of the recognition of the
location of everyone I thought that
story that was that person's name I've
lost him it's weird ever but his face
got scrambled about being in the river
everyone's in the river resentment it
was the resentment story Evers in the
river that they're in and no one has an
obligation to do more than than in fact
just orient in the right direction and
take the stuff that they can take right
it's funny that if everyone did just
that everything changes Wow I thought
okay thank you I was just I was just
feeling moved by and it was a good place
to end it off I want to say thank you to
join for your time and answering all
these questions and all the great
questions I came about so I couldn't get
to all of them I know it's getting past
11:00 in case people have to run I do
want to plug on an event that's
happening tonight
it's called seduce / steal that culture
it's on the website but the stolid got
see a there are many many more events
throughout this weekend that you can
check up on that website as well and I
think here and I have youth stoah as a
gift to all of you and if you do want to
support the store as a gift as well you
can check out the store at CA / gift to
learn more about that pass it off to
Peter if you have anything last things
to say nope I'm good thanks so much Phil
for kicking ass today that was awesome
and Jordan for coming on
Kroger km at gmail.com Shira yeah so
thanks everyone for coming home that was
that's great here's that link which one
turn to the ubi and consciousness I it's
long and it's already and I'm not sure
it's gonna be ready step a cup of tea
but it was what I was just reading and
somebody asked me to link to it